Tejbir Wason

tejbirwason.com



Software Engineer

SKILLS SUMMARY

Ever since I discovered the world of programming in university, I've been fascinated. No other profession lets you instantly see what you create. Few others have as many resources for self-learning. I've since accrued roughly **two years of work experience** and **four years of personal projects** in topics ranging from **web development** to **testing automation** to **interface design**. I'm proficient in Java, Ruby (Rails), Python, JavaScript (Node, Angular), and C++. Past employers have described me as an eager and quick learner, friendly, a strong communicator, and hard working. My graduation date is **May 2016**.

WORK EXPERIENCE

SDE, Intern Amazon.com Winter 2015

Inventory Planning and Control - Simulation, Seattle WA, USA

- Pioneered testing automation for the inventory simulation team. Designed an A/B testing framework, using
 Java to perform end-to-end simulations and compare results for quick reporting. Reduced number of man
 hours needed for testing from 2 weeks to less than a day, drastically improving workflow for downstream
 teams
- Full code ownership of framework and design of DynamoDB data stores; optimized to handle the large data passed around during simulations, along with integration to upstream data sources

Software Developer, Intern Alcatel-Lucent Summer 2014 Web Portal. Ottawa ON. Canada

- Built a SpringMVC app to calculate and quote cost of deploying Alcatel equipment. Consolidated a complex business problem into a simple web workflow for creating detailed quotes for customers worldwide
- Reduced number of client hours required to create deployment quote from 3 business days to two hours. Today a sizable proportion (~25%) of Alcatel's €14.4 billion revenue flows through this quotation tool
- Designed along with another intern entire UI/UX and coded the responsive web frontend using HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, Bootstrap and jQuery. Implemented backend function of linking an equipment configuration to a specific location for localized labor costs with real-time currency updates

Software Engineer, Intern Broadcom Corporation Summer 2013 Android Platform Quality Assurance, Richmond BC. Canada

- Developed Python scripts to utilize adb (android debug bridge) commands for stress-testing android devices with Broadcom SOC (System-On-Chip) inside them
- Constructed extensive test suites for wifi, battery, bluetooth, file transfer performance. Tests were designed to
 be capable of adapting to a varying range of devices like mobile, tablets, set-top box (pre-release FireTV).
 Also implemented a Perl-based web reporting tool to auto generate and analyze the result of continuously
 scheduled runs
- Routinely performed investigation of Android-level system termination and stress. Collaborated with chip
 designers for generating weekly performance summaries. Visualized some key metrics that proved to be
 insightful for upper management

ENTREPRENEURIAL WORK EXPERIENCE

Founder Aug 2015 – Present

Aviarry, Community world map (www.aviarry.com)

- Developed a web service to that allows users to build a community-centric world map. Heavily used Ruby on Rails on backend features including custom authentication, maps integration
- Designed and coded for the responsive mobile and web front-end using HTML5, CSS3, CoffeeScript and JavaScript. Implemented AWS workload balancing and auto-scaling strategies to handle daily traffic spikes

Founder

July 2014 – Aug 2014 (2 months)

MyJam, Winner, Startup Weekend Ottawa (www.myjam.co)

• Led winning project team at Startup Weekend Ottawa 2014. Prototyped a mobile app that allows creation of real-time collaborative playlists for parties. Leading pitch, best design and overall winner at SW Ottawa.

Project shelved for launch in Fall 2016

Founder May 2014 – Present

Capacious Labs, Personal rapid-design digital product lab (www.capacious.ca)

- Product warehouse for rapid prototype development that helps me learn about new technologies quickly and ship useful tools often
- BeerHiest A Node.js app that uses a Scrapy crawler that scrapes a popular beer store website to display
 options for the cheapest beer per unit dollar you spend
- CrookedBlue A Discourse (Rails) app to serve as an online social commonplace for UBC students. Utilized
 a lightweight Vagrant development environment and deployed using Docker image on DigitalOcean for easy
 resource management

Co-Founder, Operations Strategy Lead

Aug 2010 - May 2011 (10 months)

Xerocopy Limited, Photocopy meets advertisement (Chandigarh, India)

- Part of a founding team that bootstrapped a novel advertising channel that utilized xerox copies as advertising space for local businesses
- Spearheaded growth in client base through referrals, eventually on-boarded 35 commercial businesses. Led
 a large multi-functional team (~20 employees) with a clear daily operational strategy that helped grow profits
 two-fold in the first six months

EDUCATION

Software Engineering, University of British Columbia

Sept 2011 – May 2016 (expected)

- Bachelor of Applied Science, 7/8 academic terms completed; GPA 3.7
- Notable course projects include a real time tweet analyzer showing geographical spread of breakout stories (AngularJS, AWS), disaster response iOS app with messaging in absence of cellular signal using Apple's Multipeer Connectivity Framework (Swift, Firebase) alongside a disaster management web dashboard (NodeJS, Firebase), Android sketching game that helps enhance working memory (Java), etc.

AWARDS

- Dean's Honor List, University of British Columbia, BC, 2012, 2013, 2014 excellent academic standing based on combination of GPA and percentile rank
- UBC TREK Excellence Scholarship, University of British Columbia, BC, 2012 academic scholarship for top percentile students after first year engineering
- Youngest Winner of Startup Weekend across Canada, June 2014
- Outstanding International Student Award, University of British Columbia, BC, 2011 scholarship for meritorious performance in academics, sports and extra-curriculars
- **President's Entrance Award**, University of British Columbia, BC, 2010 entrance scholarship based on grade 12 academic performance
- Prestigious rank in All-India Engineering Entrance Exam (4747 of 1 million candidates), Chandigarh, India,
 2010– entrance scholarship based on grade 12 academic performance

EXTRACURRICULARS

UBC Golf Club

- President (Sept 2014 Present) initiated constitution of student club for golfers. Led the executive team to strategically grow size to 250 members, fastest growing club in the school's history
- As Treasurer (Sept 2013 Aug 2013) drafted annual budget for club. Planned and coordinated student tournaments with the TheFirstTee youth golf program, raising \$10000 with all proceeds going to charity
- As Webmaster (Sept 2014 Present)- coded and managed entire online presence of club to help ease onboarding and spread word to potential members

Misc. Side Coding

- Hackathons Partook in (and occasionally won) various events including Open Data, CODE, Global Game Jam and Startup Week Hackathon. Pushed personal boundaries by learning WebGL, OpenGL, Swift, Go.
- Hacked on various small projects to solve personal problems including daily mini-journal app (AngularJS), automatic login script for university website (JavaScript), scraping and messaging for a daily juice recipe (Beautiful Soup, Twilio)